片名：《断背山》
1963年，怀俄明锡诺镇
烂车！
Shit.
如果你们两个小子想找工作
You pair of deuces lookin' for work...
我建议你们立刻滚进来
I suggest you get your scrawny asses in here pronto.
在断背山上
(Aguirre) Up on Brokeback...
森林管理局标有露营区
the Forest Service has got designated campsites... on the allotments.
离羊群放牧地有三、四英里
Them camps can be 3, 4 miles from where we pasture the woollies.
晚上没人看守 掠食动物就会来
Bad predator loss if there's nobody lookin' after 'em at night.
我要的是一名营地看守员
Now, what I want is a camp tender...
待在营地，管理局指定的地方
to stay in the main camp, where the Forest Service says.
不过牧羊人 就要在羊群旁搭帐篷
But the herder he's gonna pitch a pup tent on the QT with the sheep...
还要睡在那里，晚餐
and he's gonna sleep there.
和早餐在营地吃 但百分之百…
You eat your supper and breakfast in camp...
要跟羊群睡
but you sleep with the sheep 100%.
不准生火，不能留下痕迹
No fire, don't leave no sign.
每早收帐篷 免得被管理局抓包
You roll up that tent every mornin'... in case Forest Service snoops around.
喂？
Yeah?
不
No.
不行
No!
你这辈子都甭想
Not on your fuckin' life.
你有狗有枪，你睡在那里
You got your dogs, your .30-30, you sleep there.
去年夏天我损失了近25%
Last summer I had goddamn near 25% loss.
我不想再发生那种情况
I don't want that again.
你
You.
周五中午，下山到桥边
Fridays at noon, be down at the bridge...
带着你的购物清单和骡子
with your grocery list and mules...
有人会带着补给品在那等着
and somebody with supplies will be there at the pick-up.
明早我们会载你们到出发点
Tomorrow mornin' we'll truck you up to the jump-off.
杰克特斯
Jack Twist.
艾尼斯
Ennis.
你有名没姓啊？
Your folks just stop at Ennis?
戴尔玛
Del Mar.
幸会，艾尼斯戴尔玛
Well, nice to know you, Ennis Del Mar.
我第二年来这
My second year up here.
去年一场暴风雨 闪电杀死了42只羊
Last year, one storm, the lightnin' killed 42 sheep.
我以为那味道会薰死我
Thought I'd asphyxiate from the smell.
老板很抓狂 好像我该控制天气
Aguirre got all over my ass, like I was supposed to control the weather.
不过这比帮我老爸做事要好
But beats workin' for my old man.
根本无法讨好我老爸，不可能
Can't please my old man, no way.
所以我才玩牛仔竞技 玩过吗？
That's why I took to rodeoin'. You ever rodeo?
我是说，偶尔玩玩
You know, I mean, once in a while.
一等我口袋里有钱报名就去
When I got the entry fee in my pocket.
是啊，你是牧场的人？
Are you from ranch people?
本来是
Yeah, I was.
你父母逼你离开？
Your folks run you off?
不，他们自己先走的
No, they run themselves off. There was...
43英里处有个转弯，他们没注意
one curve in the road in 43 miles, and they miss it.
所以
So
银行拿走牧场，兄姊养大我的
the bank took the ranch and my brother and sister, they raised me, mostly.
妈的，真惨
[lighter clicking] Shit, that's hard.
能不能…
Can I? Thank you.
别让它们跑丢了 老板会宰了你
(Basque) Don't let them stray. Joe will have your ass if you do.
只有一件事，别订购汤
Only thing, don't never order soup.
汤罐很难打包
Them soup boxes are hard to pack.
我不喝汤
Well, I don't eat soup.
小心点，那匹马很容易被吓到
You wanna watch it there. That horse has a low startle point.
没有马能抛下我，走吧
Doubt there's a filly that could throw me.
除非你打算整天坐着打绳结
Let's git, unless you wanna sit around tyin' knots all day.
快走！
Come on
该死
Oh, shit.
我等不及要建立自己的牧场
Can't wait till I get my own spread...
也不用再听老板废话了
and I won't have to put up with Joe Aguirre's crap no more.
我存钱想买个自己的地方
I'm savin' for a place myself.
艾玛和我，等我下山就结婚
Alma and me, we're gonna get married when I come down off this mountain.
那个跟羊睡，不准生火的规矩
Shit, that stay with the sheep, no fire bullshit.
老板无权逼我们违反规定
Aguirre got no right makin' us do somethin' against the rules.
不要再吃豆子了！
No more beans.
走啊！
Yup
妈的！该死！
Damn. Shit!
好了
I don't know.
有问题吗？
Something wrong?
有，为什么没奶粉跟蕃茄？
Yeah, so what.... Why didn't we get the powdered milk and the spuds?
我们只有这些
That's all we got.
这是下礼拜要的东西
Well.... Here's next week's.
我以为你不喝汤
Thought you didn't eat soup.
我受够豆子了
Yeah, well, I'm sick of beans.
现在厌烦豆子太早了点
Too early in the summer to be sick of beans.
走啊！
Come on.
走！走啊！
Come on. Come on.
回来，你们这些畜牲
Hold on. Whoa, whoa!
靠
Shit.
继续走
Whoa. Come back here!
过来，你们这些畜牲
Whoa there, whoa. All right. Fuck it.
你个混蛋
(Ennis) Okay, you bastard.
你跑去哪了？
Where the hell you been?
整天跟羊混，下来这里
Been up with the sheep all day, I get down here hungry as hell...
饿的半死，却只能找到豆子
and all I find is beans.
怎么回事？
What in the hell happened, Ennis?
碰上一头熊，就这样
I come on a bear is what happened.
该死的马抓狂
Goddamn horse spooked and the mules took off...
骡子跑了，食物散落地上
and scattered food everywhere.
我们也只剩豆子了
Beans is about all we got left.
有酒吗？
Got whiskey or somethin'?
蠢骡子
Dumb-ass mule.
我真不敢相信，该死
I can't believe that. God damn.
我看看
Let me see.
妈的
Shit.
我们得解决食物的问题
Well, we gotta do somethin' about this food situation.
我干脆杀一只羊好了
Maybe I'll shoot one of the sheep.
要是老板发现怎办？
Yeah, what if Aguirre finds out, huh?
我们应该要守护羊，不是吃羊
We're supposed to guard the sheep, not eat 'em.
你是怎么了？羊有上千只耶
What's the matter with you? There are a thousand of 'em.
我还是吃豆子吧
I'll stick with beans.
我才不要
Well, I won't.
好耶！
[whooping] Yeah!
受不了你老是打不中
Gettin' tired of your dumb-ass missin'.
快动手 猎杀麋鹿可不能被逮到
[laughing] Let's get a move on. Don't want the Game and Fish to catch us with no elk.
好，走吧
Come on. Shit.
我每天通勤四小时
Yeah, I'm commutin' four hours a day.
早上来吃早餐，再回羊群那里
I come in for breakfast, I go back to the sheep.
晚上整顿好它们
Evenin', get 'em bedded down.
再来吃晚餐，再回羊群那里
Come in for supper, go back to the sheep.
大半夜都在察看草原狼的踪迹
Spend hAlf the night checkin' for damn coyotes.
老板没权利逼我做这些
Aguirre got no right to make me do this.
要换班吗？ 我不介意陪羊群睡
You wanna switch? I wouldn't mind sleepin' out there.
不 重点是我们都该睡在这营地
That ain't the point. The point is, we both ought to be in this camp.
那个小帐篷又臭的跟猫尿一样
Goddamn pup tent smells like cat piss or worse.
我不介意待在那里
I wouldn't mind bein' out there.
我很高兴跟你换班
Well, I'm happy to switch with you...
不过我警告你，我不大会烹饪
but I warn you, I can't cook worth a damn.
不过我很会开罐头
I am pretty good with a can opener, though.
那你不会比我糟，好了
You can't be no worse than me, then.
给
Here you go.
我告诉你 你可没多少时间可睡
You won't get much sleep, I'll tell you that.
是啊
Yup.
走吧
Come on.
杀了一只草原狼，有够大只
Shot a coyote up there.It's a big son of a bitch.
它的蛋蛋有苹果那么大
He had balls on him the size of apples.
看来它吞得下一头骆驼
He looked like he could eat himself a camel.
你要热水吗？
You want some of this hot water?
都给你吧
It's all yours.
我没玩过多少次牛仔竞技
I don't rodeo much myself.
骑牲口八秒有啥意义？
I mean, what's the point... of ridin' some piece of stock for eight seconds?
钱就很有意义
Money's a good point. True enough.
那倒没错 要是你没被踩扁的话
If you don't get stomped winnin' it, huh?
是啊，我老爸以前是骑牛的
Well, my old man, he was a bull rider.
谢谢
Thank you.
他那时候还挺有名的
Pretty well-known in his day.
虽然他守口如瓶
Though he kept his secrets to himself.
他没指导过我 也没看过我骑牛
Never taught me a thing, never once come to see me ride.
你兄妹有好好养你吧？
Your brother and sister do right by you?
他们尽力了，我父母死后
They did the best they could after my folks was gone.
什么都没留
Considerin' they didn't leave us nothin'...
只剩一个装了24元的咖啡罐
but $24 in a coffee can.
让我念了一年高中
I got me a year of high school.
那是在车子的变速器坏掉之前
That was before the transmission went on the pickup.
之后我姐嫁给油工 搬去凯斯柏
And then my sis left. She married a roughneck, moved to Casper.
我和我哥，我们
And me and my brother...
我们去沃兰附近的牧场工作
we went and got ourselves some work on a ranch up near Worland.
到我19岁为止
Till I was 19.
他结婚了，没地方给我住
Then he got married. And no more room for me.
那就是…我来这里的原因
That's how come me end up here.
什么？
What?
这比你过去两礼拜说的话还多
Man, that's more words than you've spoke in the past two weeks.
我一年差不多就说这么多话
Hell, that's the most I've spoke in a year.
不过我爸，他是个好牛仔
But my dad, he was a fine roper.
他不大玩牛仔竞技
Didn't rodeo much, though.
他认为搞牛仔竞技的都是蠢蛋
He thought rodeo cowboys was all fuck-ups.
才不是呢！
The hell they are.
恩
Well....
你看吧
[whooping] There you go.
我刺它肚皮 向看台上的妹挥手
I'm spurrin' his guts out! Wavin' to the girls in the stands!
它想把我踢上天，却甩不掉我
He's kickin' me to high heaven, but he don't jackboard me! No!
我想我爸是对的
I think my dad was right.
帐篷看来不大对
Tent don't look right.
它又不会跑，随便吧
Well, it ain't goin' nowhere. Let it be.
那口琴的声音也不大对
That harmonica don't sound quite right either.
因为马儿甩下我时压扁了它
That's 'cause it got kind of flattened when that mare threw me.
你不是说它甩不掉你
I thought you said that mare couldn't throw you.
那是它走运
She got lucky.
如果我走运 那口琴就该被压烂
Yeah, well, if I got lucky, that harmonica would've broke in two.
我知道我该在最后一天去见你
(Jack) @ I know I shall meet you on that finAl day @
全能的主啊，带我走
@ Water-walking Jesus, take me away! @@
唱的好
Very good. Oh, yeah.
我妈，她相信圣灵降临
My mama, she believes in the Pentecost.
是吗？
Oh, yeah?
圣灵降临到底是什么？
What exactly is the Pentecost?
我父母…他们是美以美教徒
I mean, my folks, they was Methodist.
圣灵降临
The Pentecost.
我不知道，我不知道那是什么
I don't know, I don't know what the Pentecost is.
我妈没跟我解释过，我猜是…
Mom never explained it to me. I guess it's when the world ends...
我们这种人 末日降临时得下地狱
and fellas like you and me, we march off to hell.
那是你的想法
Speak for yourself.
你也许是罪人 不过我可还不是
You may be a sinner, but I ain't yet had the opportunity.
谢谢
Thank you.
谢谢你
[bottle clinking] (Ennis) Shit!
该死，我要去羊群那里了
I'm gonna go up to the sheep now. (Jack) Give 'em hell.
不，我……
[slurring] No, I'm....
你根本站不稳，现在去太晚了
You can hardly stand. It's too late to go to them sheep.
你有多一条毯子吗？
Well, you got an extra blanket?
我在这窝着，小睡一下
I'll just roll up out here, grab 40 winks...
天一亮就回去
and I'll ride out at first light.
火一灭你就会冻死
You'll freeze your ass off when that fire dies down.
这个好
Oh, that's good.
你最好睡帐篷里
You're better off sleepin' in the tent.
是啊
Yeah.
好吧
All right.
艾尼斯
Ennis!
怎样？
What?
别打颤了，快进来
Just quit your yammerin' and get in here!
你干嘛？
(Ennis) What are you doin'?
晚餐见
See you for supper.
好，走了
Yeah. Come on.
快
Come on.
这只是一次意外事件
This is a one-shot thing we got goin' on here.
这是我们之间的事
It's nobody's business but ours.
你知道我不是同志
You know I ain't queer.
我也不是
Me, neither.
对不起
I'm sorry.
没关系，没关系
It's all right. It's all right.
躺下来吧
Lie back. Come on.
特斯，你叔叔哈洛德肺炎住院
Twist. Your Uncle Harold's in the hospitAl with pneumonia.
医生说他撑不过去了
Docs don't expect he'll make it.
你妈要我来通知你
Your ma sent me to tell you,
我就来了
so here I am.
真是坏消息
Bad news.
我想我在山上也无能为力了
There ain't nothin' I can do about it up here, I guess.
你下山也帮不上什么忙
There's not much you can do about it down there, neither.
除非你会治肺炎
Not unless you can cure pneumonia.
如果我今晚不回去 羊群会乱跑
Them sheep will drift if I don't get back up there tonight!
这种风暴会把你吹跑的
You'll get pitched off your mount in a storm like this.
到时你肯定后悔
You'll wish you hadn't tried it!
快关上
It's too cold! Close it up!
我们现在该怎么办？
What are we supposed to do now, huh?
快进去
Get on in there
分开我们跟智利人的羊
and untangle 'em Chilean sheep out of ours, I guess.
在哪里？该死！
Oh, where is it? Shit!
有一半的标志都磨掉了
God, hAlf the goddamn paint brands have wore off!
我们尽量设法，保有老板的羊
We gotta try. The least we can do is get the count right for Aguirre.
去他的老板
Fuck Aguirre! Oh, yeah, fuck Aguirre.
万一我们还要靠他赏饭吃呢？
What if we need to work for him again? You think of that?
我们得继续做下去
We gotta stick this out, Jack.
你不安静点，会把羊又吓跑
You'll run them sheep off again if you don't quiet down.
你干嘛？
What are you doing?
老板又来过了
Aguirre came by again.
他说我叔叔没死
Says my uncle didn't die after all.
还说要带羊群下山
Says bring 'em down.
为什么？现在才八月中
Bring 'em down, why? It's the middle of August.
说有太平洋风暴要来
Says there's a storm comin', movin' in from the Pacific.
会比这个还猛
Worse than this one.
那场雪不过才下了一小时
That snow barely stuck an hour. Huh?
那混蛋还要砍我们一个月的钱
Besides, that son of a bitch, he's cuttin' us out a whole month's pay.
这不对
It ain't right.
那么
Well...
我能借你钱 如果你需要钱的话
I can spare you a loan, bud, if you're short on cash.
等到镇上我就拿给你
Give it to you when we get to SignAl.
我不需要你的钱 我没穷成那样
I don't need your money, huh? You know, I ain't in the poorhouse. Shit!
好吧
All right.
该上路了，牛仔
Time to get goin', cowboy.
过来，这又不是牛仔竞技
Come here! This ain't no rodeo, cowboy!
该死
(Jack) Oh, shit!
艾尼斯…艾尼斯
Ennis. Ennis.
过来，你没事了
Come here. You okay? You okay? Yeah.
有些羊根本没跟你们一起上去
Some of these never went up there with you.
我也不想数了
Count ain't what I'd hoped for, neither.
你们这些牧场工，实在不怎样
You ranch stiffs, you ain't never no good.
催点油下去
Wanna give it some gas?
我真不敢相信 我把衬衫留在上面
I can't believe I left my damn shirt up there.
是啊
Yeah.
明年夏天你还要来吗？
You gonna do this again next summer?
也许不会吧
Well, maybe not.
我说过 我跟艾玛十一月要结婚
Like I said, me and Alma is gettin' married in November.
我会设法找个牧场去做事
So... I'll try to get somethin' on a ranch, I guess.
你呢？
And you?
可能会去我爸那里，帮忙过冬
Might go up to my daddy's place and give him a hand through the winter.
若没被抓去当兵 我可能会回来
I might be back. If the Army don't get me.
我想我们后会有期了
Well, I guess I'll see you around, huh?
是啊
Right.
你看什么看！
What the fuck are you lookin' at? Huh?
宽恕我们的罪过
(Minister) ''And forgive us our trespasses...
如同我们宽恕别人
''as we forgive those who trespass against us.
不让我们陷于诱惑 但免于凶恶
(all) ''Lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from eviI.
国度、权柄、荣耀，永是您的
''For thine is the kingdom, the power and the glory, forever.
阿门
Amen.''
仅依我被授与的权力
Under the powers vested in me...
我现在宣布你们结为夫妻
I now pronounce you man and wife.
你可以亲吻新娘了
You may kiss the bride.
你若不亲，我就要亲了
And if you don't, I will.
你还好吧？
You all right? No.
住手！拜托，不要啦！
Stop! No, please don't!
我老妈想叫我辞掉工作
(Timmy) My old lady's tryin' to get me to quit this job.
她说我年纪太大了
She says I'm gettin' too old
我的背会受不了铲柏油的粗活
to be breakin' my back shovelin' asphAlt.
我告诉她我们家的人背很强壮
I told her strong backs
就是意志力太薄弱
and weak minds runs in the family.
她不认为那很好笑
[laughing] She didn't think that was too funny.
我叫她别把我养太肥
I told her it keeps me fit.
进来
Yeah!
看看风把谁吹来啦
Well, look what the wind blew in.
老板
Hi, Mr. Aguirre.
我在想你今年夏天 需要帮手吗？
I was wonderin' if you was needin' any help this summer.
你来这里是浪费时间
You're wastin' your time here.
你不需要？断背山上不缺人？
What, you ain't got nothin'? Nothin' up on Brokeback?
我没工作可以给你
I ain't got no work for you.
艾尼斯戴尔玛没来过吧？
Ennis Del Mar ain't been around, has he?
你们在山上过的还真逍遥
You boys sure found a way to make the time pass up there.
特斯，你们自己快活让狗看羊
Twist...you guys wasn't gettin' paid to leave the dogs
钱不是那样赚的
baby-sit the sheep...while you stemmed the rose.
现在，给我滚出我的拖车去
Now get the hell out of my trailer.
女儿们还好吧？
How my girls doing?
还好，珍妮还是在流鼻水
All right. Jenny's still got a runny nose.
老公，擦一下小艾玛的鼻子
Ennis, could you wipe Alma Jr.'s nose?
要是我有三只手就可以
If I had three hands, I could.
过来，过来
Come here. Come here. Oh!
女儿们还好吧？
Girls all right?
还好，珍妮不咳了
Yeah. Jenny stopped her coughin'.
我这个周末该带女儿去城里
I think I should take the girls into town this weekend.
给她们吃点冰淇淋什么的
Get 'em an ice cream. Somethin'.
我们不能搬去城里吗？
Can't we move to town?
我厌倦这些偏僻的老牧场了
I'm tired of these lonesome old ranches.
艾玛跟珍妮根本找不到玩伴
No one's around for Junior to play with.
何况我很替珍妮担心
Besides, I'm scared for Jenny...
担心她气喘的问题再发作
scared if she has another one of 'em bad asthma spells.
不行，城里的房租太贵了
No, rent in town is too high.
瑞文顿洗衣店附近有便宜房子
There's a cheap place in Riverton, over the Laundromat.
我可以把它弄的温暖舒适
I bet I could fix it up reAl nice.
你想的话，这里也做得到
I bet you could fix this place up reAl nice if you wanted to.
我知道你也会喜欢的
Ennis. Hmm? I know you'd like it, too.
真正的家园，孩子们还有玩伴
ReAl home, other kids for the girls to play with.
不像你小时候那么孤单
Not so lonely like you were raised.
你也不想那么孤单吧？
You don't want 'em to be so lonely, do you?
是啊
Yeah.
过来
Come here.
这样就不会太孤单了吧？
It ain't so lonely now, is it?
你确定女儿都睡啦？
Are you sure the girls are asleep?
确定
Yeah.
过来
Come here.
艾尼斯
Ennis.
放手一搏！这个可快了！
(male announcer) Let 'er rip and snort, boys!
杰克特斯，生死一瞬间
Jack Twist, hangin' on for dear life!
他掉下来了 小心点，他来了
And down he goes! Watch out there, fella!
小丑上场
He's comin' for you.
特斯先生表现不俗
Send in the clowns!
该死！
Okay, a fine ride by Mr. Twist. Shit!
他撑了四秒
Four seconds for him.
大家捧个场，我们的牛仔小丑
Give 'em a hand, folks, our very own rodeo clowns!
一杯啤酒就好
Give us a beer, Doug.
我请金宝喝杯啤酒
I'd like to buy Jimbo here a beer.
他是我见过最棒的牛仔小丑
Best damn rodeo clown I've ever worked with.
谢了，要是我让我救过的人
No thanks, cowboy. If I was to let every rodeo hand I pulled a bull off of...
都请我喝酒 我早就酒精中毒了
buy me liquor, I'd have been a Alcoholic long ago.
引开牛只是我的工作
Pullin' bulls off of you buckaroos is just my job.
你省下钱报名下一回竞技吧
So save your money for your next entry fee, cowboy.
你试过套小牛吗？
You ever try cAlf ropin'?
我看起来有那么行吗？
Do I look like I can afford a fuckin' ropin' horse?
我们要不要靠近一点？
Shouldn't we move a little closer?
不，不要，珍妮会吓到
{male announcer chattering] No. Come on, let's don't. Jenny'll get scared.
看看这群人
Look at this crowd!
这种人潮之中一定有很多辣妹
Bound to be a lot of pussy on the hoof in a crowd like this.
全都饥渴的等着猛男来泡
(biker #2) All swelled up with patriotic feeling...
你想最辣的妹都在哪？
and ready to be humped like a frog. So, where do you figure the most pussy is at?
拉斯维加斯还是加州？
[baby crying] Las Vegas or California?
我不知道
Hell, I don't know...
但蒙大拿跟怀俄明 我选怀俄明
but if you make it between Montana and Wyoming, I'd take Wyoming--
请小声一点 我两个小女儿在这
Hey! You might want to keep it down, I got two little girls here.
去你的，混蛋
Fuck you. Asshole.
可能生小孩以后 就不上他老婆了
Probably quit givin' it to his wife after his kids was born.
都是那样的啦
[laughing] You know what that's like. Yeah.
艾尼斯，我们走远一点 我不想惹麻烦
Ennis, let's move. Let's just move, okay?
你们嘴巴放干净点，听见没？
Now, I don't want any trouble from you. You need to shut your slop-bucket mouths, you hear me?
你该听你老婆的话
You ought to listen to your old lady, then.
是吗？
Is that right?
对，到别的地方去
Yeah. Move somewhere else.
怎样，你想被打断牙齿吗？
What about it? You wanna lose about hAlf your fuckin' teeth, huh?
今晚不想，我不想
Not tonight, bud. I'd sure rather not.
她来了 各位，看她飞快的样子
Here she comes, ladies and gentlemen! Oh, boy, look at her fly!
这是来自德州的萝琳纽森
This is Lureen Newsome from right here in ChiIdress, Texas!
让她听听我们的掌声
Come on, folks, she's gotta hear it, let's give her a big hand!
她转向第二个桶子
She's turnin' on two!
第三个
She's around three!
快点，快点
Come on, folks! Help her home!
快，大家快帮她加油
Come on! Come on!
十六秒半
And the time is 16 and 9!
接着是怀俄明来的夏安族人
Here's Cheyenne Hodson from Cody, Wyoming!
来把，女孩们
Come on, girl!
加油，她朝向第二个桶子
She's headed around two!
来自怀俄明！表现真赞！
Is there anybody here from Wyoming?
小姐
Ma'am.
这个怎么样
How about it, folks?
加油，夏安族
Come on, Cheyenne!
她的时间是十七秒二
And her time is 17 and 2!
接着是德州来的史考帝
Here comes Scotty Griffiths, out of Lubbock, Texas.
加油，史考帝…糟糕！
Come on, Scotty!
大家给史考帝热烈的掌声
Damn it! Let's give Scotty Griffiths a big hand, folks.
祝下次好运，牛仔
Better luck next time, cowboy.
这种日子还真凄惨啊
Boy, I tell you, folks, what a heck of a way to make a living!
接下来是杰克特斯
Next up is an up-and-comer!
来自怀俄明州
Jack Twist from all the way up in Lightning Flat, Wyoming.
他骑上了睡美人
He's onboard Sleepy today!
希望他不会出事
Let's hope he's not!
好，他出来了
Okay! There they go, folks!
看看睡美人，老天
And look at Sleepy go, boy!
它今天被人制住了
He's broke free today, folks!
快啊，转圈、快转圈
Come on, spin and spin and spin!
骑的好，牛仔 看裁判们怎么说
Oh, boy! Good ride, cowboy! Well, let's see what the judges say!
我敢说这是今天的赢家
I tell you, folks, that sure looked like the winnin' ride to me!
你认得那个女的？
You know that girl?
当然，萝琳纽森
I sure do. Lureen Newsome.
她爸卖农场设备，很贵的那种
Her dad sells farm equipment. I mean, big farm equipment.
价值十万元的曳引机之类的
$100,000 tractors, shit like that.
你在等什么，求偶讯号吗？
What are you waitin' for, cowboy? A matin' call?
@ No one's gonna love you like me @
@ No one else, can't you see? @
@ No one, no one @
@ No one's gonna love you like me @
@ I know sometimes you felt @
@ So lonely @
@ I know @
@ You felt so sad and blue @@
等一等
Oh, wait, hold on.
你不会认为我太猴急了吧？
You don't think I'm too fast, do you?
也许我们该踩煞车？
Maybe we should put the brakes on?
不论快慢 我喜欢你要去的方向
Fast or slow, I just like the direction you're goin'.
你还真性急
You are in a hurry.
我爸很性急
My daddy's the hurry.
他会半夜等我开车回家
He expects me home with the car by midnight.
过来、过来
Come here, come here.
你好，蒙洛
Hi, Monroe.
你好，艾尼斯
Hey, Ennis.
艾玛在吗？
Is Alma here?
在，她在调味料区
Yeah, she's in the condiments aisle.
什么？
The what?
蕃茄酱那里
Ketchup.
谢了
Thanks.
借过
(man) Your boy gonna play again this year?
是啊，借过
(Alma Jr.) Excuse us! Yeah, excuse me.
老公？你们跑来干嘛？
Hey, honey. Honey, what are y'all doing here?
事出紧急
Big hurry.
我老板要我去牧场一趟
My boss called and, well, he wants me to go up to the ranch.
母牛们突然决定要一起生小牛
Mama. I guess all the heifers must've decided to cAlve at the same time.
我把女儿都带来给你
I figured I could drop the girls off with you.
我还有很多事要做，不能离开
Ennis, well... I got a million things I gotta do here before I can leave.
我还有三小时才下班
I don't get off for another three hours.
妈妈，我要蜡笔
Mama, I need crayons.
现在不行
Not now, Alma.
拜托，你答应今晚带她们的
Ennis, please, you promised you'd take them tonight.
母牛生产，我不能不去
Alma, I can't afford not to be there when the heifers cAlve.
要是出差错，我的工作就完了
Right, it'd be my job if I lose any of 'em.
那我的工作呢？
What about my job?
好，我问我妹能不能照顾她们
Okay, all right, I'll call my sister. I'll see if she can take 'em. All right. All right.
好，你们要乖乖听妈的话喔
You be a good girl for your mama, all right?
我晚上会带点牛排回家
I'll be hAlf the night. Bring home some ground steaks if you think of it.
过来
[baby shrieking] Come here.
艾玛，天哪
Oh, Alma, please!
老天
Oh, boy.
蒙洛，真对不起
Okay. Monroe, I'm so sorry.
没关系，艾玛
It's okay. It's okay, Alma.
我会清干净 叫我妹来带走孩子
I'll clean this up just as soon as I call my sister... to come get the girls.
真的，没关系，我来就好
Really, Alma, it's okay. I'll get it.
艾玛，跟我来
Alma, come with me.
小心脚步
Watch your feet.
艾玛
Alma.
跟我一样
It's just like my hand.
女儿，有个惊喜送给你
(Jack) Honey, got a surprise for you.
嗨
(Lureen) Hey.
我带了两大箱牛奶送你
I got two whole boxes of formula for you.
120罐
You did? 1 20 cans.
120罐？
1 20?
老爸，东西放在哪里？
L.D., where did you put 'em?
我就放车子后座
Oh, hell, back seat of the car, where I left 'em.
牛仔小子可以去搬
Rodeo can get 'em.
老爸 我看得出小巴比长的像谁
L.D., I can Already see who little Bobby looks like.
好女儿
Good job, little girl.
他长的真像他爷爷
He's the spittin' image of his grandpa.
他长的真像他爷爷，不是吗？
Isn't he just the spittin' image of his grandpa?
看看那对眼睛
(Lureen) Look at those eyes.
嗨
Hey.
老婆
(Ennis) Hey, honey.
艾尼斯 你认识一个叫杰克的？
Hey, Ennis, you know somebody, name of Jack?
也许吧，怎么了？
Maybe. Why?
你有张明信片
'Cause you got a postcard. It come generAl delivery.
（朋友好久不见，24日造访）
（还在的话捎个讯来，杰克）
他是你同事，还是什么的？
Is he somebody you cowboyed with, or what?
不，杰克，他是玩牛仔竞技的
No, Jack, he rodeos, mostly.
我们以前是钓鱼的伙伴
We was fishin' buddies.
（当然在）
你也可以帮那个着色
(Alma) You can color that one, too.
我来给海滩着色
(Alma Jr.) I'll color the beach.
也许我们可以请个保姆
Maybe we could get a baby-sitter.
什么？
Huh?
带你朋友上馆子？
Take your friend to the Knife and Fork?
杰克不爱上馆子 我们只会出去
No, Jack ain't the restaurant type.
喝一杯，如果他有来的话
We'll more likely just go out and get drunk. That's if he shows.
再吃一口 然后就可以不用吃了
Okay, we take one more bite, and then you're finished with dinner.
咬一大口，很好，你可以走了
There, that's a good bite. All right, you're excused.
拜托…谢谢你
Please. Thank you.
该死的杰克特斯
Jack fuckin' Twist.
这个混蛋
(Jack) Son of a bitch.
过来
Come here.
艾玛，这是杰克特斯
Alma, this is Jack Twist.
杰克，这是我老婆艾玛
And, Jack, this is my wife, Alma.
你好
Howdy.
Hello.
你有孩子？
You got a kid.
对，两个女儿，小艾玛和珍妮
Yeah, I got two little girls. Alma Jr. and Jenny.
我有个儿子
I got a boy.
是吗？
Yeah?
八个月大
Eight months old.
很爱笑
Smiles a lot.
我娶了德州最美的女人
I married the prettiest little gAl in ChiIdress, Texas.
真的？
Yeah? Lureen.
萝琳 我跟杰克要出去喝一杯
So me and Jack, we're gonna head out and get ourselves a drink. Yeah?
当然
Sure enough.
幸会，夫人
Pleased to meet you, ma'am.
我们要叙旧 今晚可能不会回来
We might not get back tonight... when we get to drinkin' and talkin' and all.
艾尼斯？
Ennis?
你能不能帮我买条烟？
Would you get me a pack of smokes?
你要抽烟 我蓝色衬衫口袋里有
If you need smokes, Alma, they're in the top pocket of my blue shirt.
就放卧房
There in the bedroom.
四年了…靠！
Four years. Damn!
是啊，四年了
Yeah, four years.
没想到还能有你的消息
Didn't think I'd hear from you again.
是啊
Yeah
我以为你气我打你那拳
I figured you were sore from that punch.
第二年夏天，我回去断背山
Right next summer, I drove back up to Brokeback.
找老板谈工作 他说你没回去过 所以我就走了
Talked to Aguirre about a job, and He told me you hadn't been back,so I left.
去德州参加牛仔竞技
Went down to Texas for rodeoin'.
在那认识了萝琳
That's how I met Lureen.
那年才赚2千元，差点饿死
Made $2,000 that year, bull ridin'. Nearly starved.
萝琳她老爸赚的是大钱
Lureen's old man makes serious money,
卖农耕机械的
farm machine business.
他当然讨厌我
Of course, he hates my guts.
你没被抓去当兵？
And the Army didn't get you? No, too busted up.
没，牛仔竞技这行也变样了
And rodeoin' ain't what it was in my daddy's day.
趁没残废赶快退出
Got out while I could still walk.
我发誓 我不知道我们还会重逢
Swear to God, I didn't know we was goin' to get into this again.
好吧，我承认 我一路飞车赶来
Yes I did. I red-lined it all the way. I couldn't get here fast enough.
你呢？
What about you? .
我？我不知道
Me? I don't know I don't know.
断背山撮合了我们，对吧
OId Brokeback got us good, don't it?
我们现在该怎样？
What are we gonna do now?
我想可能不能怎样吧
I doubt there's nothin' we can do.
我被困在这里
So now I'm stuck with what I got here.
只能努力过生活
Makin' a livin' is about all I got time for now.
我跟杰克要去山上一两天
Well, me and Jack is headed up the mountain for a day or two.
去钓个鱼
Do ourselves a little fishin'.
你跟你朋友可以进来喝杯咖啡
You know, your friend could come inside, have a cup of coffee.
他是从德州来的
Well, he's from Texas.
德州人不喝咖啡吗？
Texans don't drink coffee?
你确定那个领班不会炒了你？
You sure that foreman won't fire you for takin' off?
那个领班，他欠我的
You know, that foreman, he owes me.
我去年耶诞还冒着暴风雪上工
I worked through a blizzard last Christmas. You remember that?
何况我只去两天
Besides, I'll only be a couple of days.
带条鱼给我，爸爸，一条大鱼
Bring fish, Daddy. A big, big one!
过来
Come here.
去吧
过来
Come here.
最迟周日见
See you Sunday, latest.
我饿坏了，要不要吃点东西？
I'm starvin'. Want to get somethin' to eat?
好
Yup.
看谁先下水！
(Ennis) Last one in!
天堂里有什么有趣的事吗？
Is there anything interestin' up there in heaven?
我只是做个感谢的祈祷
Well, I was just sending up a prayer of thanks.
谢什么？
For what?
感谢你没带口琴来
For you forgettin' to bring that harmonica.
我很享受这份宁静祥和
I'm enjoying the peace and quiet.
你知道可以就像这样 直到永远
You know it could be like this, just like this, Always.
是吗？你怎么知道？
Yeah? How do you figure that?
如果你我去某个地方 弄个小牧场
What if you and me had a little ranch somewhere...
养点牛 那种人生应该会很美好
a little cow-and-cAlf operation? It'd be a sweet life.
去他的，萝琳的老爸
I mean, hell, Lureen's old man...
他很想给我一笔钱打发我
you bet he'd give me a down payment to get lost.
他多少提过这件事
I mean, he more or less Already said it.
不…我跟你说 不会是那样的
No, I... I told you it ain't gonna be that way.
你有老婆孩子
You know... you got your wife and baby in Texas.
在德州 我在瑞文顿有我的人生
You know, I got my life in Riverton.
是吗？
Is that so?
你跟艾玛，那就算人生了？
You and Alma, that's a life?
不准你批评艾玛 这不是她的错
Now you shut up about Alma.This ain't her fault.
最重要的是
The bottom line is...
我们拥有彼此，而这件事
we're around each other...
再度让我们聚首
and this thing grabs hold of us again...
换个错误的地点和时间
in the wrong place... in the wrong time...
我们就死定了
and we're dead.
我告诉你
I tell you...
以前我家乡有两个老家伙
there were these two old guys ranched up together down home.
厄尔和瑞奇 他们是镇上的笑柄
(Ennis) Earl and Rich. And they was a joke in town...
尽管他们…
even though they
他们是很坚毅的老鸟
were pretty tough old birds.
总之厄尔死在灌溉壕沟里
Anyway, they found Earl dead... in an irrigation ditch.
有人拿铁撬打昏他，拖着他
They took a tire iron to him, spurred him up...
绑住他的小弟拖到拉断为止
and drug him around by his dick till it pulled off.
你亲眼看到了？
You seen this?
对，我当时九岁
Yeah, I was what? Nine years old.
我爸坚持要带我跟我哥去看
(Ennis) My daddy, he made sure me and my brother seen it.
就我所知，他也有份
Hell, for all I know, he done the job.
两个男人住在一起，不可能
Two guys living together? No way.
我们现在可以偶尔碰头
Now, we can get together once in a while...
找个偏僻的地方就行，不过…
way the hell out in the middle of nowhere, but....
偶尔？每四年一次？
''Once in a while.'' Every four fucking years?
如果你无法改变，就得忍受它
Well, if you can't fix it, Jack, you gotta stand it.
忍多久？
For how long?
直到我们驯服它为止
(Ennis) As long as we can ride it.
这是匹无法驾驭的马
There ain't no reins on this one.
晚餐时间到了，你要去哪？
(Ennis) It's nearly suppertime. Where the hell do you think you're going?
去上班
(Alma) To work!
我以为你今天休假
I thought you had the day off!
你搞错了
Well, you thought wrong!
女儿要吃饭
The girls need to be fed.
你自己搞定吧
Well, you take care of it!
艾玛！艾玛！
Alma! Alma!
晚餐在炉子上
Supper's on the stove!
你不上菜没人会吃
No one's eatin' unless you're servin' it!
我已经答应要加班了
I Already promised I'd take the extra shift!
告诉他们你弄错了
Fucking tell 'em you made a mistake, then!
该死，艾玛！
God damn it, Alma! Alma!
你们需要人帮忙推吗？
You girls need a push or somethin'?
不用
(both) No.
你们听 凯迪拉克都没这种声音
(Jack) Listen to her purr, gentlemen!You ain't gonna get that with your Caddy!
我提过它的功能 让我展示一下
I told you what she could do, and now let me show you.
那家伙以前不是骑牛的吗？
(farmer) Say, didn't that pissant used to ride the bulls?
他只是“尝试”过
He used to try.
老婆 你有看到我蓝色夹克吗？
[door closing] Honey, have you seen my blue parka?
我上次看到时，是你穿着它
(Lureen) Last time I seen it, you was in it...
那天刚好有大风雪来袭
day we had that big ice storm.
我发誓我在这看过它
Well, could have sworn I seen it in here.
你知道
You know...
你这些年老是去怀俄明
you've been going up to Wyoming all these years.
为什么 你朋友不能来德州钓鱼？
Why can't your buddy come down here to Texas and fish?
因为大角山不在德州
Because the Bighorn Mountains ain't in Texas.
我也不认为他的破车 能开这么远
And I don't think that his pickup could make it down here, anyway.
新型设备这周会到，记得吗？
(Lureen) New model comin' in this week, remember?
你是我们的最佳业务员
You're the best combine salesman we got.
你才是超级业务员
You're the only combine salesman, in fact.
我一周内就回来，除非我冻死
Yeah, I'll be back in a week. That is, unless I freeze to death...
没找到夹克 我就真的会冻死了
and I'll freeze if I don't find that parka.
我没拿你的臭夹克
Well, I don't have your goddamn parka.
你掉东西时的脾气比儿子还差
You know, you're worse than Bobby when it comes to losin' stuff.
说到儿子，你跟学校联络了？
Well, speakin' of Bobby, did you call his school... about gettin' him a tutor?
我以为你会联络
I thought you were gonna call.
我太会抱怨了
I complain too much.
老师不喜欢我，该你联络了
That teacher don't like me. Right. Now it's your turn.
好吧
Okay, fine,
我晚点会联络
so I'll call later.
好
Right. Fine.
拜，我还有14小时的车要开呢
Goodbye. (Jack) Got 1 4 hours of driving ahead of me.
看吧，这似乎不大公平
See now, it don't seem fair...
你一年去那里两三趟
you goin' up there two, three times a year...
他却从未来过这里
with him never comin' down here.
电力公司有缺，薪水可能不错
Ennis, they got an opening over at the power company. Might be good pay.
我笨手笨脚的 搞不好会被电死
Well, as clumsy as I am, I'd probably get electrocuted.
爸，下周末教会野餐
(Alma Jr.) Daddy, the church picnic's next weekend.
到时你钓鱼回来了吗？
Will you be back from fishing by next weekend?
爸，拜托嘛
[grunts] Please, Daddy? Please!
好吧，只要不逼我唱歌就去
Well, all right, as long as I don't have to sing.
爸爸，谢谢你
Daddy. Thank you.
你是不是忘了什么？
You forgettin' somethin'?
你迟到了
(Jack) You're late.
你看我带了什么来
(Ennis) Look what I brought.
豆子？
beans.
是啊，我要像往日一样煮豆子
This way.
很好，我没帮你了
There you go! No hands!
全是你在开呢，巴比
(Jack) It's all yours, buddy! It's all yours.
来啊、来啊
Come on, come on.
今天是周六夜
It's Saturday night,
我们可以打扮一下去教堂晃晃
and head on over to the church sociAl.
去给那群人折磨？
That fire and brimstone crowd?
我觉得应该不错
I think it'd be nice.
艾尼斯
Ennis.
我们过得
As far behind as we are on the bills...
这么入不敷出的
it makes me nervous
没避孕让我很紧张
not to take no precaution.
如果你不想再生孩子
If you don't want no more of my kids...
我很乐意放过你
I'll be happy to leave you alone.
我愿意生，如果你愿意养的话
I'd have 'em, if you'd support 'em.
两名小孩的监护权
(judge) Custody of the two minor chiIdren...
小艾玛和珍妮归原告
Alma Del Mar Jr. and Jennifer Del Mar... is awarded to plaintiff.
被告必须支付原告养育费用
Defendant is ordered to pay chiId support to plaintiff...
每个小孩每月125元
in the sum of $1 25 per month for each of the minor chiIdren...
直到她们满18岁成年为止
untiI they reach the age of 18 years.
戴尔玛夫妇离婚获准
Del Mar divorce granted,
1975年11月6日
this sixth day of November, 1975.
（进入怀俄明州）
上车吧
In you go.
你来这干嘛？
What are you doin' here, huh?
我收到你离婚的信息了
I got your message about the divorce.
过来
Come here.
这位是杰克
Well, this here's Jack.
杰克，我女儿小艾玛和珍妮
Jack, these are my little girls.There's Alma Jr. and Jenny. Hi.
快打招呼，女儿
Say hi, girls. (both) Hi.
我收到你说你离婚的卡片
I got your card that the divorce came through.
是啊
Yeah.
所以…我就来了
So here I am.
我沿路问很多人你搬去哪了
I had to ask about 10 different people in Riverton... where you had moved to.
这个嘛
En……
我以为那代表你…
I guess, I thought that this means you....
杰克，我不知道该说什么
No, Jack, I don't know what to say.
这周末我女儿过来跟我过
See, I got the girls this weekend and....
我相信你明白我有多抱歉
Jeez, I.... I'm sure as hell sorry. You know I am.
我一个月才能见她们一次
See, I only get them once a month,
我上个月错过了
and I missed last month.
所以我…因为我去赶集畜牲
So I just.... Because of the roundup.
所以
So....
这个嘛
Well....
是啊，好吧
Yeah, all right.
杰克
Jack.
那我下个月再来看你了
I'll see you next month, then.
（墨西哥边界，68英里）
先生？
[speaks Spanish]
来了
(Lureen) Comin' up.
上桌了
Here we go. Here we are!
等等，牛仔
Whoa there, Rodeo.
老丈人在此，我来切
The stud duck do the carvin' around here.
当然，我只是…想帮你省麻烦
You bet, LD. I was just saving you the trouble.
巴比
Bobby,
你不吃晚餐，我就关掉电视
if you don't eat your dinner.I'm gonna have to turn off that television.
为什么？
Why, Mama?
反正接下来两周我都要吃剩菜
I'm gonna be eating this food for the next two weeks.
你听见你妈的话了
Hey, you heard your mama.
吃完饭，你才能看球赛
You finish your meAl, and then you can watch the game.
爸？
Daddy?
Daddy.
我们又不是用眼睛吃饭
Hell, we don't eat with our eyes.
你希望你儿子长大成人吧？
(L.D.) You want your boy to grow up... to be a man, don't you, Daughter?
男生就该看足球
[clearing throat] Boys should watch football.
除非他吃完晚饭
Not untiI he finishes eating the meAl...
那是他妈妈花了三小时准备的
that his mama took three hours to fix.
你给我坐下，混帐东西
Now you sit down, you old son of a bitch!
这里是我家，这是我的小孩
This is my house, this is my chiId...
而你是我的客人
and you are my guest. Now you sit down...
你坐好，免得我动手赶人
before I knock your ignorant ass into next week.
爸，说说你骑野马的事吧
Daddy, tell about when you rode broncs in the rodeo.
那故事很短
Well, that's a short story, honey.
那才三秒，我骑在野马背上
It was only about three seconds I was on that bronc.
接着我就飞过空中
The next thing I knew, I was flying through the air...
可是我不是天使
only I was no angel
不像你跟珍妮一样
like you and Jenny here.
我没有翅膀
I didn't have no wings.
那就是我的驯马生涯
And that's the story of my saddle bronc career.
好了
There you go.
你该再婚的，艾尼斯
You ought to get married again, Ennis.
我跟女儿们都担心你一个人
Me and the girls worry about you bein' alone so much.
一朝被蛇咬…
Well, once burned....
你还跟杰克去钓鱼吗？
You still go fishing with Jack Twist?
不常
Not often.
我曾怀疑你为何从不带鱼回家
You know, I used to wonder how come you never brought any trouts home.
你老说你钓了很多
You Always said you caught plenty...
而你也知道我跟女儿都爱吃鱼
and you know how me and the girls like fish.
所以有一晚，我打开你的鱼箱
So, one night, I got your creel case open...
就在你们某次钓鱼之前
night before you went on one of your little trips.
五年了，价格标签却还在
Price tag still on it after five years.
而我在另一端绑了一个字条
And I tied a note to the end of the line.
上面写“老公，带点鱼回家”
It said, ''Hello, Ennis, bring some fish home. Love, Alma.''
后来你回家
And then you come back lookin' all perky...
神采奕奕的 说你抓到一堆鳟鱼
and said you caught a bunch of brownies and you ate them up.
还把它们都吃了，你记得吗？
Do you remember?
我去检查箱子，我的字条还在
I looked in that case first chance I got... and there was my note still tied there.
标签线完全没碰过水
That line hadn't touched water in its life.
那不代表什么
That don't mean nothing, Alma.
别想再骗我了
Don't try and fool me no more, Ennis.
我知道那代表什么，那个杰克
I know what that means. Jack Twist.
艾玛
Alma.
龌龊杰克！你们才不是去钓鱼
Jack ''Nasty''!You didn't go up there to fish.
你跟他
You and him--
你给我听着，你啥都不知道
Now you listen to me, you don't know nothing about it
我要叫蒙洛了
[crying] I'm going to yell for Monroe.
你叫啊 我会让他好看
You do it and I'll make you eat the fucking floor.
出去！
Get out!
出去！出去！你也一样
And you, too! Get out! Get out!
出去！滚出我家！ 你听见了！滚出去！
Get out of my house, Ennis Del Mar! You hear me? You get out!
爸？
Daddy?
出去！
[dishware shattering]
艾玛？你还好吧？
Alma?
拜，爸
(Jenny) Bye, Daddy!
拜！
(Alma Jr.) Bye.
混蛋，走路要看路
Hey, asshole, watch where you're goin'!
搞什么！老天
Jesus. What....Jesus....
你这个混帐东西
(driver) You stupid fuck!
该死的混蛋
God damn!
去你妈的！你该死！
God. God damn.Oh, fuck!
该死！
Damn it!
我是说
All I'm sayin' is
那有什么意思？就算没缴税
what's the point of making it?If the taxes don't get it,
通货膨胀也会吃光利润
the inflation will eat it all up.
你该看萝琳算钱的样子
You should see Lureen punchin' numbers in her adding machine.
她打着计算机，找寻额外的0
Hunting for extra zeros,
她的眼睛越眯越小
her eyes gettin' smaller and smaller.
就像看一只兔子
It's like watchin' a rabbit tryin' to...
想躲进蛇洞里避难似的
squeeze into a snake hole with a coyote on its taiI.
那真是上流社会的娱乐
That's some high class entertainment, if you ask me.
一切都很值得
For what it's worth.
你跟萝琳，你们正常吧？
You and Lureen, it's normAl and all?
当然
Sure.
她没起过疑心？
She don't ever suspect?
你有没有过一种感觉
You ever get the feelin'...
我不知道
I don't know...
当你进城，有人看着你
when you're in town... and someone looks at you...
用怀疑的眼光 好像他知情似的
suspicious, like he knows.
然后你走在人行道上
Then you go out on the pavement and everyone's lookin' at you...
大家看你的眼光 好像啥都知道
like they all know, too?
也许你该离开那里了
Well, maybe you ought to get out of there, you know?
找个不一样的地方 也许德州？
Find yourself someplace different, maybe Texas.
德州？
Texas?
当然，也许你能说服艾玛
Sure, and maybe you can convince Alma...
让你跟萝琳认养我女儿
to let you and Lureen adopt the girls.
然后我们就能住一起，养羊
Then we could just live together, herdin' sheep.
你那有钱的岳父
And it'll rain money from L.D. Newsome...
会把钱给我们 溪里流着威士忌
and whiskey will flow in the streams.
杰克，那太聪明了
Jack, that's reAl smart.
你去死吧，艾尼斯
Go to hell, Ennis Del Mar.
你想悲惨度日，那就请便
You wanna live your miserable fucking life? Then go right ahead.
好
Fine.
我只是说出我的想法
I was just thinkin' out loud.
是啊，你想的还真周到
Yup, you're a reAl thinker there. God damn....
唬烂杰克，事事都想得周全
Jack fucking Twist. Got it all figured out, ain't he?
我刚下班，要跳舞吗？
Just finished my shift. Wanna dance?
我正要去…
I was on my way to the--
我是凯希，凯希卡芮
I'm Cassie. Cassie Cartwright.
艾尼斯戴尔玛
Ennis. Del Mar.
我不要再跳舞了
No more dancin' for me, I hope.
你安全了
You're safe.
什么？
Yeah?
我的脚痛
My feet hurt. H
工作很辛苦啊？
ard work, is it?
是啊，像你这种醉鬼一直点酒
Yeah, drunks like you demanding beer after beer...
又抽烟，真令人讨厌
smokin'. Gets tiresome.
你是做什么的，艾尼斯？
What do you do, Ennis Del Mar?
我今早还在阉牛呢
Well, earlier today, I was castrating cAlves.
你干嘛？
What are you doing?
想要人给我按摩一下脚，笨蛋
Trying to get a foot rub, dummy.
好吧…那样行吗？
All right. That good?
我在南美以美大学加入姊妹会
And then I pledged Tri Delt at SMU.
从未想过最后会到这个小地方
And I sure never thought... I'd end up in a poky little place like ChiIdress.
然后我在农工大学认识老朗代
Then I met old Randall here at an Aggie game...
他主修畜牧，所以我们到过这
and he was an animAl husbandry major.
来了一个月，他去牧场做工头
So we've been here for a month and he got the foreman job over at Roy Taylor's ranch. Like it or not, here I am!
无论如何，我就在这里了！
Was you Tri Delt? I was Kappa Phi myself.
你参加过姊妹会？ 那是我死对头 虽然我们不大像姊妹会的
Well, even though we ain't quite sorority sisters...
不过我们得把彼此当舞伴
we just may have to dance with ourselves, Lureen.
我们的丈夫都对跳舞不感兴趣
Our husbands ain't the least bit interested in dancin'.
他们甚至连节奏感都没有
They ain't got a smidgen of rhythm between them.
很好笑，对吧？
It's funny, isn't it?
丈夫通常都不跟老婆跳舞
Husbands don't never seem to wanna dance with their wives.
你想那是为什么呢？
Why do you think that is, Jack?
我从来没想过这点
I don't know, I never give it any thought.
要跳舞吗？
Wanna dance?
好，谢谢  你介意吗？
Yes, thank you. (Jack) Do you mind?
当然不  去吧
No, it's all right. Go ahead. All right.
谢谢你邀我跳舞
(LaShawn) Pardon us. Thank you for asking me to dance with you.
我很感激，真的
I really appreciate that. Randall never does.
你跟萝琳能碰巧遇见我们真好
Last time I did, I think it was our wedding. It's a good thing you and Lureen happened along when you did
不然我们还蹲在路边呢
or else we'd still be stuck on the side of the road... in that darn pickup.
我跟朗代说该买车 他老是不听
I told Randall we ought to take the car. Of course, he'd never listen to me.
他就是不听我的 好像耳聋似的
[laughing] He wouldn't listen to me if he was goin' deaf tomorrow.
我跟他说 他根本修不好那辆破车
I told him it'd take more than chewing gum and baling wire... to fix that pickup.
他本来就不会修车
Well, he's never been very mechanicAl, though.
过来
Come over here and ask....
你注意到 女人参加派对前会扑粉
You ever notice how a woman will powder her nose... before she goes to a party?
派对结束后又会再扑粉吗？
And then she'll powder it again once the party's over.
都要回家睡觉了还扑什么粉？
I mean, why powder your nose just to go home and go to bed?
不知，就算我想知道
Don't know. Even if I wanted to know...
我也插不上我老婆的话去问
I couldn't get a word in with Lashawn long enough to ask.
女人讲话就像连珠炮
Woman talks a blue streak.
真有元气的女人
Lively little gAl.
你喜欢帮洛伊干活吗？ 他很可靠 是啊，他是个好人
You'll like working for Roy Taylor. He's solid, Roy. Yeah, Roy. He's a good old boy.
他在坎普湖畔有栋小木屋
He's got a little cabin down on Lake Kemp.
一间小房子、一艘小船
Got a crappie house, little boat.
还说我想用时随时都能用
Said I could use it whenever I want.
我们该找个周末去一趟
We ought to go down there some weekend.
喝点威士忌、钓个鱼
Drink a little whiskey, fish some.
远离喧嚣，你知道的
Get away, you know?
那是在大学毕业后
(LaShawn) That was right out of SMU.
我选择在北达拉斯找工作
I could've had my pick of pretty much any job in North Dallas.
所以我选了尼曼马可斯 那真糟
So my pick was Neiman Marcus, which was a disaster...
因为只要有漂亮衣服
because, honey, where clothes is concerned, I got no resistance.
我就无法抗拒，花的比赚的多
I was spending more than I made. More than Randall ever will make.
比朗代赚的还多 那时我们来此
We come out here... thinkin' that ranchin' was still big hats and Marlboros.
觉得牧场的人还土的半死
Boy, were we behind the times.
小艾玛，准备好了？
(Ennis) Hey there, Junior. You ready?
你觉得怎样？
(Cassie) What do you think?
你爸有想再成家吗？
Your daddy ever gonna see fit to settle down again?
不知，也许他不适合婚姻
Don't know. Maybe he's not the marrying kind.
你不这么想？
You don't think so?
还是你不认为我适合他？
Or you don't think I'm the one for him?
你算不错了
You're good enough.
你话不多，却很坦白
You don't say much, but you get your point across.
抱歉，我无意失礼
Sorry. I didn't mean to be rude.
好了
All right.
你踩到我的脚了，牛仔
You're stayin' on your feet, cowboy.
对不起，亲爱的
Excuse me, darling.
我下周末去接你跟珍妮吧
So I'll pick you and Jenny up next weekend,
做完礼拜之后
after church.
好
Fine.
你还好吧？
You all right?
很好
Yes.
你确定？
Are you sure?
爸，我在想那个新宝宝的事
Daddy, I was thinking, what with the new baby and all...
妈和蒙洛对我很严
Ma and Monroe have been awful strict on me.
比对珍妮还严
More on me than Jenny even.
我在想，也许我可以
I was thinkin', maybe I could....
我可以跟你一起住
Maybe I could come stay with you.
我会是个好帮手，我知道的
I'd be an awful good help, I know I would.
你知道，我没办法过那种生活
Now, you know I ain't set up for that.
等我去赶牲口时，就不会在家
With the roundup comin'... I won't ever be home.
没关系，爸
It's all right, Daddy.
我不是说我不想
I'm not sayin' that I wouldn't--
没关系，我明白
It's all right, I understand.
那就周日见了
Well, see you on Sunday, then.
拜
Bye.
拜，乖女儿
Bye, sweetheart.
今晚肯定会下雪
Going to snow tonight for sure.
是啊
Yup.
这些日子 你还没找到再婚对象？
All this time and you ain't found nobody else to marry?
我跟镇上一个美女在交往
I been puttin' the blocks... to a good-lookin' little gAl over in Riverton.
她是个服务生
She's a waitress.
想去念护校之类的
Wants to go to nursing school or somethin'.
我不知道，你跟萝琳呢？
I don't know. What about you and Lureen?
萝琳很会谈生意
Lureen's good at making hard deAls in the machinery business...
不过我们的婚姻状况
but as far as our marriage goes...
讲讲电话就行了
we could do it over the phone.
我跟一个牧场工头的老婆有染
I kind of got this thing going with... a ranch foreman's wife over in Rutters.
每次我溜去见她
What? I'm bound to get shot...
都可能被活逮毙命
by Lureen or her husband each time I slip off to see her.
你可能也活该
You probably deserve it.
告诉你
Tell you what.
事实上
The truth is...
有时我好想你，想到无法承受
sometimes I miss you so much, I can hardly stand it.
我想我会回老家去一两天
I guess I'll head up on to Lightning Flat.
看看我父母
See the folks for a day or two.
我有话一直想告诉你
There's somethin' I been meanin' to tell you, bud.
等我们十一月运走牲口之前
Well, it's likely November before I can come out here again.
我都不会有空再来这 在冬季饲养开始之前
After we ship stock and before winter feedin' starts again.
十一月
November.
是啊
Yup
那八月怎么办？
What in the hell ever happened to August?
好把
Well....
天哪，艾尼斯
Christ, Ennis.
你有一个礼拜可以告诉我的
You know, you had a fucking week to say some little word about this.
我们干嘛老到这么冷的地方
Why is it we're Always in the friggin' cold?
我们该去温暖的南方
We ought to go south where it's warm, you know!
我们应该要去墨西哥
We ought to go to Mexico.
墨西哥？
Mexico?
杰克，你知道我的
Hell, Jack, you know me. About all the travelin' I ever done...
我从来没去过多远的地方
is around a coffee pot, looking for the handle.
拜托，杰克，别逼我
(Ennis) Come on, Jack. Lighten up on me.
我们可以在十一月打猎
We can hunt in November.
猎只大麋鹿
Kill us a nice elk.
我会设法再跟老唐借小木屋
I'll try if I can get Don Wroe's cabin again.
我们那年很快乐，对吧？
We had a good time that year, didn't we?
时间永远不够，永远不够
There's never enough time, never enough.
这该死的状况真令人不满
You know, friend... this is a goddamn bitch of an unsatisfactory situation.
你以前出来都很轻松
You used to come away easy.
现在却像晋见教宗一样
Now it's like seein' the Pope.
杰克，我得工作
Jack, I got to work.
早些年，我会干脆辞了工作
In them earlier days, I'd just quit the job.
你忘了贫穷日子的感觉了
You.... You forget what it's like bein' broke all the time.
你听说过扶养子女吗？
You ever hear of chiId support?
我告诉你，我不能辞掉这工作
I'll tell you this, I can't quit this one...
我也不能请假
and I can't get the time off.
这次已经够难了，得牺牲八月
It was hard enough gettin' this time. The trade-off was August.
你有更好的主意吗？
Well, you got a better idea?
我有，曾经
I did, once.
曾经？
(Ennis) You did, once.
你到过墨西哥了？
Well, have you been to Mexico, Jack Twist?
我听说墨西哥有服务你们的人
'Cause I hear what they got in Mexico for boys like you.
我是到过那里，有问题吗？
Hell, yes, I've been to Mexico. Is that a fucking problem?
我只打算告诉你这一次
I'm going to tell you this one time, Jack fucking Twist.
我不是笨蛋
And I ain't foolin'.
那些你背着我做 我不知道的事
What I don't know, all them things that I don't know...
如果我知道的话 你也别想活命了
could get you killed if I come to know them.
我可不是开玩笑
I ain't jokin'.
试试看吧，我就说这么一次
Yeah, well try this one, and I'll say it just once.
说啊
Go ahead! I'll tell you what.
我们本可以共度美好人生
We could have had a good life together.
美好人生，有个共同的家
Fucking reAl good life. Had us a place of our own!
不过你却不想要
But you didn't want it, Ennis.
现在我们只剩下断背山了
So what we got now is Brokeback Mountain!
一切都建在那之上
Everything's buiIt on that!
那是我们所拥有的一切
That's all we got, boy. Fucking all.
所以我希望你别知道实情
So I hope you know that, if you don't never know the rest!
你数数我们才在一起多少次
God damn it. You count the damn few times...
我们已经在一起20年了
that we have been together in nearly 20 years...
你紧紧拴住我 问我墨西哥的事
and you measure the short fucking leash you keep me on and then you ask me about Mexico and you tell me you'll kill me
为我追寻我得不到的东西 要杀我
for needin' somethin' I don't hardly never get!
你根本不知道这有多难受
You have no idea how bad it gets!
我不是你
And I'm not you! I can't make it...
我没办法靠那一两次撑一整年
on a couple of high-Altitude fucks once or twice a year!
你令我无法忍受，你这个混蛋
You are too much for me, Ennis. You son of a whoreson bitch!
我真希望知道该怎么离开你
I wish I knew how to quit you!
那你干嘛不离开？
Then why don't you?
你干嘛不干脆丢下我呢？
Why don't you just let me be, huh?
这全都是因为你，我变成这样
It's because of you, Jack, that I'm like this.
我什么都不是，无处可去
I'm nothin'. I'm nowhere.
没事了 少理我
It's okay. Get the fuck off me!
过来！
Come here
没关系…没事了
It's all right. It's all right.
没事了，艾尼斯
Damn you, Ennis.
我再也受不了了
I just can't stand this anymore, Jack.
来吧 你像马一样卷缩着脚睡觉
Come on now, you're sleepin' on your feet like a horse.
小时候我妈曾这么说过我
My mama used to say that to me when I was little.
还唱歌给我听
And sing to me.
我要走了，早上见
I got to go. See you in the morning.
抱歉
Excuse me.
艾尼斯戴尔玛
Ennis Del Mar.
你去哪了？
Where you been?
到处跑
Here and there.
我在牧场留过话给你
I left word for you with Steve at the ranch.
你一定有收到 我留在你家的字条
And you must've got those notes I left at your place.
看来我有没收到都无所谓
Looks like I got the message, in any case.
卡尔？卡尔很好，他会说话
Carl? Yeah, Carl's nice. He even talks.
那很好
Good for you.
是啊，是很好
Yeah. Good for me.
我真不明白你，艾尼斯
I don't get you, Ennis Del Mar.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
我可能不够风趣，对吧？
I was probably no fun anyways, was I?
让女人坠入爱河的不是风趣
Ennis, girls don't fall in love with fun.
（亡故）
喂？
(Lureen) Hello. Hello,
我是…艾尼斯戴尔玛
this is Ennis Del Mar.
谁？你是谁？
Who? Who is this?
艾尼斯戴尔玛，杰克的老朋友
Ennis Del Mar. I'm an old buddy of Jack's.
杰克曾提起过你
(Lureen) Jack used to mention you.
你是他钓鱼还是打猎的朋友
You're the fishing buddy or the hunting buddy, I know that.
我该让你知道发生了什么事
Would have let you know what happened...
不过我不确定你的姓名或地址
but I wasn't sure about your name or address.
杰克把朋友的地址都存在脑里
Jack kept his friends' addresses in his head.
所以我才打来问个究竟
That's why I'm callin', to see what happened.
是啊，杰克当时在帮轮胎打气
Oh, yeah. Jack was pumpin' up a flat on the truck...
轮胎爆炸时他就在旁边
out on a back road, when the tire blew up.
轮圈直接砸中他的脸
The rim of the tire slammed into his face...
砸断他的鼻梁和下巴
broke his nose and jaw
还把他砸的当场昏倒
and knocked him unconscious on his back.
等有人发现他时
By the time somebody come along,
他已经被自己的血给淹死了
he'd drowned in his own blood.
他享年39岁
He was only 39 years old.
喂？
Hello? Hello?
喂？喂？
Hello.
他葬在那里吗？
Was he buried down there?
我们立了石碑
We put a stone up.
依他所愿火化了他
He was cremated, like he wanted.
一半的骨灰葬在这里
HAlf his ashes was interred here
其余的则送到他父母手上
the rest was sent up with his folks.
他曾说他想将骨灰  在断背山
He use to say he wanted his ashes scattered on Brokeback Mountain...
不过我不确定那在哪里
but I wasn't sure where that was.
我以为断背山可能在他家乡
I thought Brokeback Mountain might be around where he grew up.
够了解杰克
Knowing Jack...
就知道那可能是个想像的地方
it might be some pretend place...
那里有蓝鸟歌唱，威士忌迎春
where bluebirds sing and there's a whiskey spring.
不，夫人
No, ma'am...
我们某年夏天曾在那里牧羊
we was herdin' sheep on Brokeback one summer...
就在1963年
back in '63.
他说过那是他最爱的地方
Well, he said it was his favorite place.
我以为他喝醉了，他常喝醉
I thought he meant to get drunk. He drank a lot.
他父母是不是住莱飞镇？
Is his folks still up in Lightning Flat?
他们到死也不会离开那里的
They'll be there till the day they die.
谢谢你的说明
Thank you for your time.
我很遗憾，我们以前是好朋友
I sure am sorry. We was good friends.
跟他父母联络吧
Get in touch with his folks.
我想他们会很感激的
I suppose they'd appreciate it
如果他的愿望能实现的话
if his wishes was carried out.
我是说骨灰的事
About the ashes, I mean.
要喝杯咖啡、吃块蛋糕吗？
Want a cup of coffee, don't you? Piece of cherry cake?
好的，我喝咖啡 但吃不下蛋糕
Yes, ma'am, I'll have a cup of coffee... but I can't eat no cake just now.
谢谢
Thank you.
杰克的事我很遗憾
I feel awful bad about Jack.
谢谢
Thank you.
我无法说明我有多哀伤
I can't begin to tell you how bad I feel.
我认识他很久了
(Ennis) I knew him a long time.
我是来问一声
I come by to say that...
是否需要 我带他的骨灰去断背山
if you want me to take his ashes up there on Brokeback...
他太太说他有这个愿望
like his wife said he wanted to...
我很乐意代劳
then I'll be happy to.
我告诉你吧
I'll tell you what.
我知道断背山在哪
I know where Brokeback Mountain is.
他自以为特别 不该葬家族墓园
Thought he was too goddamn speciAl to be buried in the family plot.
杰克曾说，艾尼斯戴尔玛
(John) Jack used to say....''Ennis Del Mar,''
他曾说过
he used to say.
我总有一天要带他上去
''I'm gonna bring him up here one of these days...
我们会一起建一个牧场
''and we'll lick this damn ranch into shape.''
他有些不成熟的想法
He had some hAlf-baked notion...
说你们俩要搬上去那里
the two of you was gonna move up here...
建一栋小木屋
buiId a cabin...
一起帮忙经营牧场
help run the place.
然后今年春天
Then, this spring...
他找到另一个家伙 跟他一起上去
he got another fella gonna come up here with him...
建起一栋房子
buiId the place,
帮忙经营牧场
help run the ranch.
是他在德州做畜牧的邻居
Some ranch neighbor of his from down in Texas.
他要跟他老婆分手，回来这里
Gonna split up with his wife and come back here...
所以他说…
so he says.
不过 就跟杰克大部分的想法一样
But, like most of Jack's ideas...
永远都不成形
never come to pass.
我保留了他房间 跟小时候一样
(mother) I kept his room like it was when he was a boy.
我想他会很高兴的
I think he appreciated that.
欢迎你去他房间 若你想去的话
You are welcome to go up to his room, if you want.
好，我要去，谢谢你
Yeah, I'd like that. Thank you.
告诉你吧
(John) Tell you what.
我们有个家族墓园
We got a family plot.
他要葬在那里
He's goin' in it.
是的，伯父
Yes, sir.
你有空再回来看我们吧
You come back and see us again.
伯母
aunt
这个很谢谢你
Thank you, ma'am.
你好，小艾玛
(Ennis) Hey there, Junior.
爸爸
Hey, Daddy.
过来
Come here.
喜欢这辆车吗？
Like the car?
是你的吗？
Yeah. Is it yours?
是寇特的
It's Kurt's.
我以为你男友叫…特洛伊
I thought you were seein' Troy. Troy?
爸，那是两年前的事了
Daddy, that was two years ago.
特洛伊还在打棒球吗？
Troy still playing baseball?
不知道 我现在跟寇特在一起了
I don't know what he's doing. I'm seein' Kurt now.
那寇特是做什么的？
Well, what does Kurt do?
在油田里工作
Works out in the oiI fields.
他是油井工？
So he's a roughneck, huh? [laughing]
对
Yeah.
你19岁了，想怎样就能怎样
I guess you're 19, you can do whatever you want. Isn't that right?
当然
Sure.
爸，你需要多一点家具
Daddy, you need more furniture. Yeah, well...
一无所求，就不需要东西
if you got nothin', you don't need nothin'.
你来有什么事？
So, what's the occasion?
我跟寇特，我们要结婚了
Me and Kurt... we're getting married.
恩
Well....
你认识这家伙多久了？
So how long have you known this guy for?
大约一年了
About a year.
婚礼6月5日在美以美教会举行
Our wedding will be June 5, at the Methodist church.
珍妮会唱歌
Jenny will be singing
蒙洛会找外快的人来
and Monroe is gonna cater the reception.
这个叫寇特的…他爱你吗？
Now this Kurt fella... he loves you?
爱，爸爸，他爱我
Yeah, Daddy. He loves me.
我希望你会到
Was hopin' you'd be there.
我想我到时 正在提顿附近赶牲口
I think I'm supposed to be on a roundup down near the Tetons.
你知道吗？
You know what?
我想他们可以去找个新牛仔
I reckon they can find themselves a new cowboy.
我的小女儿
My little girl,
要结婚了
getting married.
敬艾玛，也敬寇特
To Alma and Kurt.
杰克，我发誓…
Jack, I swear....